American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- New York Office, 1855-circa 1981, undated, Series 3:; (box 17-32; 15 linear ft.)
  - Personal Papers, Memorabilia and Ephemera, 1855-1923, undated, 3.5:
    Ernest Lewis, fellow in architecture, was at the American Academy in Rome, circa 1908-1911. Little is known of him other than that he practiced architecture in New York. The Ernest Lewis scrapbook, included in this subseries, includes photographs of Lewis and his fellow students (many identified, most likely at a later date), circa 1908-1911; interior views of Mirafiore and Lewis in Egypt; photographs of architectural renderings and drawings of architectural details (some by Lewis, others unsigned); clippings and printed matter about architecture, including illustrations of a prize-winning work, and articles about French architects Constant Désiré Despradelle and Jean Louis Pascal; photographs and reproductions of architectural renderings of Roman buildings and entries in various architectural competitions; a McKim, Mead & White label [possibly a bookplate]; a reprint from The Technology Review, November 1912, of an article about Constant Désiré Despradelle; "Rome Letter," 1913 and undated, by George S, Koyle, Fellow in Architecture, American Academy in Rome; and an article about Jean Louis Pascal from Journal of the American Institute of Architects, circa 1913.
    Allan Marquand (1853-1924) was professor of art history and archaeology at Princeton University, from 1883 until his death in 1924. Between 1896 and 1897 he served as a professor in the School of Classical Studies in Rome. From approximately 1909 to 1923, he chaired the annual meeting of the Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies of the Archaeological Institute of America, a committee which originated in the School of Classical Studies. Papers relating to Marquand and included in this subseries were given to the American Academy in Rome by Miss Lucy Shoe, who had received the materials from the Marquand family.
    Charles Follen McKim (1847-1909), after studying at Harvard, and the Ecole des Beaux Arts, and working in the offices of H. H. Richardson, in 1879 formed the architectural firm of McKim, Mead, and White. After meeting other architects and artists at the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago and discussing with them the advantages of studying art in Europe, McKim proposed the idea for a school in Europe for American artists. From this plan emerged the American School of Architecture in Rome which eventually became the American Academy in Rome. In addition to being a founder, McKim served as trustee, treasurer, and president; in the early days, McKim's determined service and financial help were responsible for the institution's continued existence. Acquisition documents relating to McKim's files are contained in this subseries and include an itemized list of the gift, labeled as follows: "Documents, property of Mr. McKim, which were brought from Mr. Smith's office by Mr. Dolan (21/8/47) to be left with record in A.A.R. office (in small black case in closet)." Items 10, 11, 12 (case of drawing instruments, 18" ruler, and sketch by unknown artist) were not among the materials received from the American Academy in Rome by the Archives of American Art.
    Charles R. Morey (1877-1965) was a professor of art and archaeology at Princeton University, a fellow at the American School of Classical Studies in Rome in 1903, and professor of classical studies at the American Academy in Rome from 1925 to 1926. From 1945 to 1947, Morey served as Acting Director, and later Director of the American Academy in Rome. Morey's correspondence is included in this subseries.
    Mural painter Elihu Vedder (1836-1923), a resident of Rome, was affiliated with the firm of McKim, Mead and White during a stay in America from 1897 to 1898. Nothing is known of the circumstances under which the Elihu Vedder Bible, included in this subseries, became the property of the academy.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of individual to whom the material relates, then by subject.
    - Ernest Lewis Photograph Album/Scrapbook, circa 1908-1917 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
    - Allan Marquand Papers (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - Acquisition, 1951 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        (label from package and brief explanatory note)
      - American Institute of Archaeology, Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Archaeology, Annual Reports, 1905-1916 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - American Institute of Archaeology, Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Archaeology Minutes, 1909-1923 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - Bibliography, Introduction to Etruscan and Roman Archaeology, undated (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - Correspondence, 1896-1920 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        (concerns fundraising for archaeological fellowships, fellowship candidates, and business of the Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Archaeology of the Archaeological Institute of America)
      - History of the School of Classical Studies, circa 1909 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        (notes compiled by Marquand)
    - Charles F. McKim Memorabilia, Photographs, Printed Matter, and Artifacts (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - Acquisition (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - Memorabilia (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Business card of Charles F. McKim, Architect with Gambrill & Richardson (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Diploma, Master of Arts, Bowdoin College, undated, (stored in OV folder 36) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Resolution of the Trustees of Columbia College, November 4, 1899 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
          (thanking McKim for his gift of $20,000 to endow traveling scholarships for graduate architects; in leather presentation case, with letter of transmittal to Miss McKim, November 22, 1909)
        - Diploma, Honorary Doctor of Letters, Columbia College, 1904, (stored in OV folder 36) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Life Membership certificate, American Academy in Rome, April 25, 1905, (stored in OV folder 36) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Certificate of Election as Academician, National Academy of Design, May 8, 1907, (stored in OV folder 36) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Diploma, Honorary Doctor of Law, University of Pennsylvania, February 22, 1909, (stored in OV folder 36) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Proceedings of "University Day," University of Pennsylvania, February 22, 1909 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
          (stored in OV folder 36: program for ceremony in which McKim was presented an honorary doctor of laws degree; in personalized leather presentation binding Resolution of Society of Columbia University Architects, on the death of Charles Follen McKim, November 1, 1909)
        - Invitation to meeting of the American Institute of Architects, December 15, 1909 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
          (commemorating the life and services of Charles Follen McKim)
      - Photographs of Charles F. McKim (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Daguerreotype, circa 1855 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
          (stored in black cabinet, drawer 8: in machine-tooled leather case with red velvet lining, metal clasp, 7.5 × 6.2 cm)
        - Album, undated, 1869 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
          (contains 13 portraits, 11 cartes de visite and 2 tintypes)
      - Photographs of Others (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - James Miller McKim (father of Charles F. McKim), undated (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Unidentified Woman (possibly McKim's mother or another relative), undated (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      - Printed Matter (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Portrait of Charles F. McKim, undated (letterpress halftone) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Church, Albert E. Plates to "Descriptive Geometry," by Albert E. Church. New York, A.S. Barnes and Burr, 1865. (Box 31, Reel 5795)
          (inscribed: "Charles F. McKim, Sept. 1866, Used at Paris while preparing for L'Ecole de Beaux Arts--1867--"))
      - Artifacts [unfilmed] (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Steel printing block for McKim's monogram, undated (Box 31, Reel 5795)
        - Brass printing plate for calling card of John W. Beatty, Director, Carnegie Institute, undated (Box 31, Reel 5795)
    - Charles R. Morey Correspondence, 1920 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      (regarding the Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies of the American Archaeological Institute; also, fellowship application of Albert M. Friend, Jr.)
    - Elihu Vedder's Bible (1 wrapped package) (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      (published by B. Waugh and T. Mason, for the Methodist Episcopal Church, New York, 1833 [cover lacking]; inscribed: "Sent on from Florida rec'd in Rome, Feb. 24th, 1912 by Elihu Vedder")
  - Association of the Alumni of the American Academy in Rome, 1913-1945, undated, 3.6:
    Records of the Association of the Alumni of the American Academy in Rome (1.5 linear inches) consist of a small number of scattered records including correspondence, fellows' war/government service information (compiled by Sidney Waugh), membership lists, and a newsletter.
    - Correspondence, undated, 1913-1945 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      (includes correspondence about fundraising, invitation to participate in an exhibition to be circulated by the American Federation of Arts, nominations and elections, and form letter soliciting ideas about the direction Academy should take after World War II)
    - Fellows' War/Government Service Records (compiled by Sidney Waugh), 1946 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
      (completed forms, A-Z, correspondence, lists, etc.)
    - Membership Lists, undated (Box 31, Reel 5795)
    - Newsletter, Nov. 1919 (Box 31, Reel 5795)
  - Miscellaneous Records, 1899-1926, undated, 3.7:
    Miscellaneous records consist of writings and architectural records. Writings consist of published and unpublished manuscript material about the American Academy in Rome and its history. Two files relate to a 1922 issue of Art and Archaeology issue on the American Academy in Rome. The School of Fine Arts Section file consists of an outline indicating it was to feature articles by G. P. Stevens, F. P. Fairbanks, P. H. Manship, and Russell Cowles. The file includes the text of Stevens's article, Rome Preeminently the Center for the Advanced Study of Architecture, with illustrations; photographs of "Diogenes, detail of a composition called `The Philosophers' by Ezra Winter, Fellow in Painting of the American Academy in Rome;" and photographs of Greco-Roman sculpture to illustrate Manship's article. The School of Classical Studies Section file includes The School of Classical Studies manuscript by G. M. Wicher with illustrations, including a portrait of Tracy Peck (1838-1921), Director of the American School of Classical Studies in Rome and the school library at Via Vicenza. It also includes the manuscripts, with illustration of Literature, History and Religion, by Nelson G. McCrea, Archaeology, by A. W. Van Buren, and Publications and Museum, by C. Densmore Curtis (including a view of the Museum of the American Academy in Rome and photographs of individual items in its collections).
    Architectural records [oversize] include property and floor plans of the Villas Aurora, Chiaraviglio, Ferrari, and Ludovisi.
    - Articles about The American Academy in Rome and its History, undated, circa 1899-1926 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      (includes pieces by Frank D. Millet, Edwin H. Blashfield, William R. Mead, and Frank Miles Day, as well as many unsigned articles and fragments)
    - "Suggestions for a Beginner Undertaking a Decoration Ensemble Involving (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      (Paintings-Ornaments & Gold Work," by H. Siddons Mowbray, 1916)
    - Text and Illustrations for Art and Archaeology School of Fine Arts Section, 1922 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
    - Text and Illustrations for Art and Archaeology School of Classical Studies Section, 1922 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
    - Fragments of Unidentified Letters, undated (Box 32, Reel 5795)
    - Villa Aurora, undated (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      (stored in OV folder 37: plan of property, pen and ink drawing on architects' linen)
    - Villa Chiaraviglio, 1921 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      (stored in OV folder 37: basement plan, first-floor plan, second-floor plan, and third-floor plan, all on one sheet, blueprint)
    - Villa Ferrari, undated (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      (stored in OV folder 37: 2 plans of property, pen and ink on architects' linen)
    - Villa Ludovisi, Casiono dell' Aurora, undated (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      (stored in OV folder 37: ground floor plan, first story plan, second story plan, and roof plan, 4 pencil drawings)
- Rome Office, 1903-1947, undated, Series 4:; (boxes 32-34; 2.9 linear ft.)
  This series contains records maintained by the Rome office of the American Academy in Rome.
  Records are arranged into two subseries.
  4.1: Records of Staff: Directors and School of Fine Arts Faculty, 1903-1947, undated
  4.2: Personal Papers of Director Gorham Phillips Stevens, 1912-1931, undated
  - Records of Staff: Directors and School of Fine Arts Faculty, 1903-1947, undated, 4.1:
    This subseries consists primarily of the office files of the Rome office directors but also contains four folders of records of the School of Fine Arts faculty. The records document the administration of the School of Fine Arts, the School of Classical Studies, and their facilities in Rome. The most extensive and complete files are those of Gorham Phillips Stevens (1.25 linear feet). Records of other directors, H. Siddons Mowbray, George Breck, Jesse Benedict Carter, James Monroe Hewlett, Chester H. Aldrich, Amey Aldrich, Charles R. Morey, and Laurance P. Roberts, are quite incomplete and range in size from 1 folder to 0.5 linear feet.
    H. Siddons Mowbray's correspondence includes letters to McKim about the Villa Aurora, expenses, exhibition, and the King and Queen attending the academy opening; a letter from Charles Keck about his studio; and correspondence concerning endowment fundraising.
    George Breck's correspondence includes a letter to Secretary Millet about appraisal of the Villa Mirafiore and Madam Loyson's idea of starting a girls' school in Rome that would be a branch of the American Academy in Rome. It also includes letters from Rockefeller's secretary declining to participate in the academy's proposed endowment.
    General correspondence of Jesse Benedict Carter concerns competitions, use of the terms "fellowship" and "scholarship," an exhibition, Committee on the School of Classical Studies business, a request for extension of fellowship time, and activities of fellows. Endowment fundraising correspondence concerns Carter's lecturing activities on behalf of the academy's endowment fund and appeals to individuals for contributions. A folder concerning the Villa Mirafiore contains correspondence regarding an agreement to use the Villa Mirafiore as a hospice for mutilated Italian soldiers.
    Gorham Phillips Stevens Stevens served as director in 1912. During Carter's tenure as director, from 1913 to 1917, Stevens was director of the School of Fine Arts and served as acting director during Carter's frequent absences. He was acting director following Carter's death in 1917, and in 1919 became the director. His general correspondence includes "Suggestions for the Management of the Academy during the absence of the Director in America;" correspondence about a proposed publication; requests for museum passes; letters of introduction; inquiries about fellowship competitions; travel arrangements; letters concerning shipment of art work, concerns about war conditions, and Daniel Chester French's opinion of the proposed purchase of an enlarging machine for the sculptors; George Breck's comments on prices set by artists for their work; and letters concerning summer school, housing for women, the possibility of McKim's daughter giving his medals and diplomas to the academy, and the trustees decision to inaugurate a new educational policy under a new director.
    There is one folder of material relating to Amey Aldrich, sister of Chester H. Aldrich, who acted as an assistant and official hostess during his tenure, and probably served as acting director for a brief time following Mr. Aldrich's death. The folder includes a report on the administrative situation of the academy, ideas about closing the academy during World War II, and evaluation of staff. Material also concerns repairs to buildings, staffing, and receipts for academy funds held by Chester Aldrich and returned after his death.
    Records of the directors comprise the bulk of the subseries and are first in the subseries. Records of faculty members Frank P. Fairbanks and Felix Lamond are at the end of the subseries. Director and faculty member names are indicated in bold at the top of each file group.
    File groups for each individual begin with any general correspondence and are then arranged alphabetically by subject or name of individual to whom the file relates.
    - H. Siddons Mowbray, Correspondence, undated, 1903-1906 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
    - George Breck, Correspondence, 1906-1910 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
    - Jesse Benedict Carter (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      - General Correspondence, undated, 1913-1916 (Box 32, Reel 5795)
      - Endowment Fundraising, undated, 1912-1914 (Box 32, Reel 5795-5796)
      - Villa Mirafiore, 1916 (Box 32, Reel 5796)
    - Gorham Phillips Stevens (Box 32, Reel 5796)
      - General Correspondence, undated, 1912-1934 (Box 32, Reel 5796)
      - Academic Council Minutes, 1919-1932 (Box 32, Reel 5796)
      - Annual Report, 1916 (notes) (Box 32, Reel 5796)
      - Association of Alumni of the American Academy in Rome, 1914-1915 (includes letter about collaborative problem) (Box 32, Reel 5796)
      - Benton, Hale P. (Assistant to Director, Rome), 1926-1932 (Box 32, Reel 5796)
        (includes correspondence regarding Benton's appointment and his duties)
      - Blashfield, Edwin H. (Committee on the School of Fine Arts), undated, 1916-1928 (Box 32, Reel 5796)
        (includes correspondence about a plan for preparing a students' guide to art in Italy, fresco, war conditions, and Blashfield's love of Italy)
      - Boring, William A. (Treasurer)/Arthur H. Crane (Assistant Treasurer), 1913-1932 (Box 32, Reel 5796-5797)
        (includes correspondence concerning construction of new building, responsibility for academy finances in Carter's absence, fees connected with the sale of Villa Mirafiore, married fellows, housing)
      - Carter, Jesse Benedict (Director, Rome), undated, 1913-1917 (Box 32, Reel 5797)
        (includes correspondence about new building, Villa Aurelia; Millet's bequest of costumes, books, and photographs; staffing, housing, President Mead's visit to Rome, fellows, exhibitions, academy servants, finances and expenses, war conditions, extension of fellowship time, Carter's death; also, notes and letters from Mrs. Carter)
      - Collaborative Problem, 1916 (Box 32, Reel 5797)
      - Conferences, 1926-1930 (Box 32, Reel 5797)
        (correspondence and printed matter relating to conferences attended by Stevens: Archaeological Congress in Palestine and Syria 1926; International Archaeological Congress, Rhodes, 1928; Archaeological Institute of Germany, Berlin, 1929; International Archaeological Congress, Algeria, 1930)
      - Crane, Arthur H. (see: Boring, William A.) (Box 32, Reel 5797)
      - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1928 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
      - Del Frate, Gastone (Legal Counsel), 1913-1929 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (includes correspondence about Heyland will, taxes, Villa Aurelia)
      - Egbert, James C. (Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1922-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (correspondence concerning search for permanent head of the School of Classical Studies, fellows, housing, staffing, contributing colleges)
      - Exhibitions, 1913-1917 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (correspondence, invoices, and shipping lists concerning academy entries in the Architectural League of New York exhibitions, 1915-1917, and the Paris Salon, 1913)
      - Fairbanks, Frank P. (Professor in Charge, School of Fine Arts), 1919-1929 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (includes letters with news of Paul Manship, exhibitions, and recommendations for strengthening the academy's library)
      - Fellows, undated, 1913-1927 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (correspondence with and about current and former fellows A-Z, including suggestions for improving the Academy, rules relative to married fellows, letters of introduction, shipment of art work)
      - Frank, Tenney (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1924 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
      - Galassi Architetti, 1915-1929 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (correspondence with architects for Janiculum improvements)
      - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1920-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (includes correspondence about shipment of student work, articles for Art & Archaeology, housing, fellows, staffing, inventory of china and linens in apartments for annual professors, gifts)
      - Kelsey, Francis W. (Trustee), 1915, 1924 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (includes correspondence regarding his plans to visit Rome, recommendation that Villa Aurelia be used for embassy purposes)
      - Kendall, William M. (Trustee), 1913-1930 (Box 33, Reel 5797)
        (correspondence concerning responsibilities and titles of officers in Rome, collaborative problem, academy monuments, new building, Mead's burial in Rome with description and diagram of his cemetery plot)
      - La Farge, C. Grant (Secretary)/Wolfe, W.R. (Associate Secretary)/ Moses, Lionel (Assistant Secretary), 1912-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5797-5798)
        (includes correspondence about Stevens' responsibilities and title, married fellows, letters of introduction, collaborative problem, fellows, competitions, exhibitions, shipment of student work and packing lists, expense reduction, war conditions, gifts, fellowship in landscape architecture, extension of fellowship time, staffing, Professor Clark's war work, Art & Archaeology issue on the academy, salaries)
      - Lamond, Felix (Professor of Music), undated, 1924-1928 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence about fellows, music studios in Villa Aurelia)
      - Laurie, Charles (Bursar), 1913-1915 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
      - Library and Publications, undated, 1912-1929 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence proposing a "Letter from Rome" column for The Journal of the American Institute of Architects, correspondence about articles on the academy for other periodicals, recommendations for purchases of books on landscape architecture, book orders)
      - McClellan, George B. (Library Committee; Vice President), 1914-1930 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence concerning opinions about the war, Library Committee business, housing, salaries, Villa Aurelia expenses)
      - Mead, William R. (President), 1911-1928 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes Stevens' letter of application for the position of director, with biographical information; correspondence concerning condition of Villa Aurelia, director Carter's style of management, new building; Stanford White's son, Lawrence; endowment, exhibitions, taxes, housing, fellows, collaborative problem, international hostel in Rome for women, acquisition of property adjacent to the academy, staffing)
      - Mellon, Edward P. (Trustee; Endowment Committee), 1913-1915; 1922-1923 (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (includes correspondence concerning details of the academy fellowship competitions to be held in Paris, Polasek's activities, travel plans, new building, servants, Endowment Committee business)
      - Notes re: Castle of Bolsena and St. Peter's, undated (Box 33, Reel 5798)
        (possibly Fellows' projects)
      - Platt, Charles A. (Vice President; Acting President; Committee on the School of Fine Arts; President), 1928-1932 (Box 33, Reel 5798)